Kassoy, Bernard Papers 6385
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bernard Kassoy Papers
1928-2009
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kassoy, Bernard
6385
5.67 cubic feet
5.3 linear ft.
Papers.
8507514
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 25, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, August 27, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Bernard (Bernie) Kassoy (1914-2008) graduated from the City College of New York and Cooper Union Art School and worked in a wide range of media as a painter, printmaker, photographer, sculptor and cinematographer. As a young artist, Kassoy began his career in the WPA New York City Federal Art Project in 1936 and was arrested under the name "Michelangelo Buonarotti" at the first sit-down strike against the WPA by the Artists Union. He was also a US delegate to the 1983 International Association of Artists conference in Finland.
In 1939 Kassoy was hired as a New York City high school fine arts teacher where he taught until he retired in 1972. He also taught adult education classes on cinematography at the High School of Music and Art. As a member of the American Federation of Teachers Local 5, he created cartoons for their publication "The New York Teacher News," directed the Teachers Union art gallery, and made stage sets for theatrical productions.
Bernie Kassoy's 136 editorial cartoons preserved by the Kheel Center were largely created in the 1950s at a time when many US policy makers were enthralled by the search for Communist Party members and sympathizers. In pithy cartoons he portrayed the struggles of New York City students and teachers, as well as the Teachers Union's response to these hardships. He accused school, city, and state officials of turning their attention away from funding shortfalls, classroom overcrowding, outdated texts, dilapidated buildings, teacher turnover, increasing teacher workloads, and stagnant wages, to focus on the question of whether any teachers appeared to be advocating Communism. Though Kassoy repeatedly criticized these manifestations of McCarthyism, he was never blacklisted. His work can also be found in the collections of the Museum of Modern Art, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York Public Library, and Fennimore House Museum.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6385 F: Bernard Kassoy Films 6385 P: Bernard Kassoy Slides and Photographs 6386: Hortense Kassoy Papers 6386 P: Hortense Kassoy Slides and Photographs
8507514
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bernard and Hortense Woodcut Show, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Bernard and Hortense Exhibit Notices, 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bernard and Hortense Posthumous Exhibit, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Bernard and Hortense Lehman College, 1985-2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Press Releases, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Exhibition Leaflets and Flyers, 1962-2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Clippings (Box 1, Folder 27)
- ALA News, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Abel Meeropol Article, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- American Artists Congress, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- American Printmakers, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- American Society of Contemporary Artists (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Art Appreciation Course (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Art: USA: 58, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Artists for Nuclear Disarmament, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Artists Union Membership Card (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Associated Councils on the Arts, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Award for Gladstone Cooper (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Biographical Material, 1936-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Biographies and List of Framed Works (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Black on White: The Woodcut Poster, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Botanical Garden Project, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Bronx High School of Science, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Bronx Museum of the Arts (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Caravan House Show (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Certificates of Appreciation, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Certificate of Authenticity, 1975-2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Cinema Course, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- City College Alumni, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- City College 50th Reunion, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- College Transcripts, 1939-1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Contemporary Artists Guild, 1974-2003 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Contemporary Graphic Artists Vol. 2, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Co-op Voices, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Cooper Union (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Curriculum Vita (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Diary of Spain and Pietrasanta (Box 2, Folder 31)
- ESTA: Elders Share The Arts, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- 80th Birthday, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Exhibition Entry Fees (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Expenses, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- 50th Wedding Anniversary, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Film Class Materials, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Film Editing: GSMP 52 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Film Series (Box 2, Folder 39)
- For Julia Winston, 1978-2000 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Finland, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- For "Palette Scrapings" (Box 2, Folder 42)
- George Gilbert (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Graphic Artists Guild, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Hadassah Tour to Israel, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Harriet FeBland, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Harry Jackson (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Henry A. Wallace, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- High School of Music and Art, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- High School of Music and Arts Letterhead Designed by B. Kassoy (Box 2, Folder 50)
- IAA Member Organizations and Other Artists Groups, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- If You Want Anything At Night, Call Eddie (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Illustrations for Book by Sonya Samberg (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Kheel Center Collection, 1999-2008 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- League of Present Day Artists, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Lithography Lesson Plans, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Lou Bunin (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Master's Term Paper, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Master's Term Paper (Handwritten), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Material for Bronx Institute, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Memorial for Peretz Kaminsky (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Mentioned in Various Publications (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Michael's Menagerie, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Military Records, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- New York Public Library, 1993-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- New York State Historical Association, 1979-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- New York City WPA Art, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Notes on Lithography (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Pastel Society of America, 1981-2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Personal, 1971-2008 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Philip Reisman: A Life Remembered, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photography Notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Print Consortium, 1990-2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Prints, Mexican, in Studio, 1984-2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Reflect, Relate, Reveal, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Rosenfeld Fine Arts, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Saga of the Tour #703 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Sales (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Salon, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Scenarios and Shooting Records, 1959-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Show and Party, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Smithy-Pioneer Gallery Show, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Society for Humanistic Judaism, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Sophie-Louise Ullman Red Scare Film, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Studio Exhibits and 53rd Wedding Anniversary Sale (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Studio Painting, Richard Rodriguez, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Talk to Brush and Palette Society, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Teacher College, 1951-1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Teacher News Drawings Photocopies (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Teachers Union Local 5 "Dreamers and Fighters", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Teaching License Citations, 1937-1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- They Were Here, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- USSR Trip, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Veteran's Administration Disability (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Veteran's Administration G. I. Bill (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Virginia Center for the Creative Arts Fellowships, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Vladeck Hall Gallery, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- WPA Show, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- West Indies Cruise, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Westlake Gallery, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Who's Who and Other Published Biographies, 1970-2007 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Williams Print Collection, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Wood, Tools and Equipment for Artist-Engravers (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Correspondence, 1936-1946 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Correspondence, 2000-2007 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Correspondence: Members of Congress and Others, 1964-1987 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 47)
  Scope and Contents
  No Date
- Correspondence: Letters to Merry Kassoy, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- In Memoriam: Bernard Kassoy, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Obituaries, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Sympathy Cards, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Writings: B1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Writings: B2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Writings: B3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Writings: Other (Box 4, Folder 4)
  (Loose in B1-3 Binder)
- Poetry Drafts (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Poetry Extra Copies (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Before 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1980s [Folder 1 of 2], 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 1980s [Folder 2 of 2], 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Duplicates (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Old Papers, 1975-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Honey's Birthday and Other Cards by Bernie, 1967-1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Sketch Book (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Trip Journal: France and Italy, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Travel Journal: Mediterranean Sea, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Trip Journal: Cuba, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Travel Journal: Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Travel Journal: Virginia Center for the Creative Arts, Cruise on the Nieuw Amsterdam, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Travel Journal: Bodiman, Caribbean Cruise, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Travel Journal: England, France, and Italy (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Passports, 1959-1995 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Diaries, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Diaries, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Diaries, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Note Books (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Appointment Book, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Appointment Book, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Appointment Book, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Appointment Book, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Appointment Book, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Appointment Book, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Appointment Book, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Appointment Book, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Appointment Book, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Appointment Book, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Appointment Book, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Appointment Book, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Appointment Book, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Appointment Book, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Appointment Book, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Appointment Book, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Appointment Book, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Appointment Book, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Appointment Book, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Appointment Book, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Appointment Book, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Appointment Book, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Appointment Book, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Appointment Book, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Book of Signatures. Bernard Kassoy's Classmates, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Address Book and Ledger (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Postcards: Bernard Kassoy (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Postcards: France (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Postcards: Italy (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Postcards: USSR (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Postcards: Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous Leaflets and Flyers, 1939-1977 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Membership and ID Cards, 1962-2004 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Awards, Certificates, and Diplomas (Box 6)
  - Award, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Box
  - Certificates and Diplomas (Box 6, Folder 2)